A Guide to the Dickson Family Papers, 1769-1924
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Dickson Family Papers, 1769-1924
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Dickson family (Greenbrier County, W. Va)
Ms1998-094
2.8 Cubic Feet 2 boxes
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Dicksons were pioneer settlers of Greenbrier County, Virginia (now West Virginia). Joseph Dickson (1749-1822) settled in what is now Greenbrier County, West Virginia, from Ireland by way of Pennsylvania in the 1770s. He received land grants originally from the King's land office in 1769, and later from the Commonwealth of Virginia in 1785, 1789, and 1795 for property on Howard's Creek. His son, Robert Dickson (1795-1869?), inherited the land and built Locust Hill in 1833, now called Mountain Home. Robert Renick Dickson (1827-1888) and Henry Frazier Dickson (1841-1909), Robert Dickson's sons, inherited the land and in turn left it to their heirs. The Dicksons turned Mountain Home near White Sulphur Springs into a resort in the 1800s and early 1900s. The property and home were owned by the family until they were sold in 1968.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist largely of land, property, and goods transaction receipts and documents of each of the four generations of the family represented. Certificates, oaths, correspondence, deeds, and a diary are included in Joseph Dickson's papers, along with several slave sale documents from the late 1700s and early 1800s. Many of the land, slave, and goods exchanged were with neighbors and others in the area. Most of Joseph Dickson's documents are individually described in this inventory. The papers of John Dickson (1737-1809, brother of Joseph Dickson), Robert Dickson, Robert Renick Dickson and Henry Frazier Dickson, and Geraldine Dickson Burrow (1879-1943, daughter of Henry Frazier Dickson), are grouped by type of material (for example, financial accounts, correspondence, and land deeds). Within Robert Dickson's correspondence are a few references to the Civil War, including a letter from a Confederate tax collector demanding payment of his 1863 Confederate taxes. Other interesting documents include the transcript (1916) of the trial of Sallie Dickson (wife of Robert Renick Dickson) who was sued by Henry Frazier Dickson, for payment of rent due to him. The papers also include genealogy charts of the family.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged by family member, and then chronologically by type of material.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Local/Regional History and Appalachian South
- Joseph Dickson, 1769-1822
  - Legal Documents, 1769-1796, n.d.
    - Certificate, June 15, 1769 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Certificate asserting that Joseph Dickson was received in his parish and "has behaved himself in a Verry prudent and exemplary manner," signed by M. Johnson.
    - Certificate, June 15, 1769 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Certificate stating that Joseph Tooth knows Joseph Dickson "...to be of good respectable character...and believe him to be of untainted moral character..."
    - Certificate, March 15, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Certificate asserting that Joseph Dickson lived in Greenbrier County, Virginia, for four years and "Behaved himself as an honast man aught to Do."
    - Oath, April 9, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Oath to the General Assembly [of Virginia] taken by Joseph Dickson, signed by Geo. Skillem
    - Marriage Certificate, August 17, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Marriage certificate of Joseph Dickson and Mary Yung, married March 5, 1772, signed by McHoy(?) in Lebanontown.
    - Certificate, December 15, 1780 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Certificate signed by John Dickinson of Augusta County, Virginia, as to Joseph Dickson's good character when Dickson lived on Dickinson's land.
    - Certificate, January 22, 1785 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Certificate that Joseph Dickson resided in the Spreading(?) congregation from 1779 to 1780, and "behaved himself sober and in an inoffensive manner," signed by Edward Crawford.
    - Statement, March 13, 1790 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Statement of falsely accusing John Wevans "with taking goods out of the store of Francis Mara" made by Mary Wave.
    - Certificate, July 19, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Certificate that Joseph Dickson (son of Joseph Sr.) has lived in East Hanover, Pennsylvania, and learned the hatter trade, signed by Daniel Bradley.
    - Certificate (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Certificate of military service, signed by Capt. James Smith (n.d.)
  - Correspondence, 1775-1807, n.d.
    - From unknown, April 24, 1775 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      From unknown asking Joseph Dickson to give John Humphrys his bond.
    - Thos. Dunwody to W. Jos. Archer, March 14, 1786 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Thos. Dunwody to W. Jos. Archer about a survey of Joseph Dickson's.
    - Th. Edgar to Jos. Dixon, September 25, 1790 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Th. Edgar to Jos. Dixon about the sale of a cow; mentions W. Kyle, W. Hagreth, and W. Black.
    - William Wallace to James Black., February 20, 1792 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      William Wallace to James Black.
    - Lazarus Ainsworth to Joseph Dickson, November 20, 1793 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Lazarus Ainsworth to Joseph Dickson about payment of a sickel left in Dickson's care.
    - Th. Edgar to Joseph Dickson, May 17, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Th. Edgar of Lewisburg to Joseph Dickson acknowledging receiving a horse.
    - James Welch to Joseph Dickson, July 26, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      James Welch of Lewisburg to Joseph Dickson about dry goods sold
    - Joseph Snell to Robert McClentck(?), November 21, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Joseph Snell to Robert McClentck(?) about an ax he wants to give to Joseph Dickson.
    - Jacob Baumgardsen to Joseph Dickson, September 22, 1801 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Jacob Baumgardsen to Joseph Dickson about receiving eight pounds cash.
    - J. Patton and Jas. Richards to Joseph Dickson., November 30, 1804, April 27, 1807 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      J. Patton to Joseph Dickson for flour sold; Jas. Richards to Joseph Dickson, asking him to send a hat (?) he left for Dickson with Samuel Ruiker or Jas. Kincaid.
    - Robt. Steele(?) to Joseph Dickson, November 10, 1807 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Robt. Steele(?) to Joseph Dickson about a possible breach of contract with Miss Cathe McClung.
    - Charles Mislock(?) to Joseph Dickson (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Charles Mislock(?) to Capt. Joseph Dickson about shodding a horse and drawing blood on a sick man (n.d.).
    - Robert Humphreys to unknown (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Robert Humphreys to unknown about a bed he wishes to buy from Mr. [Joseph] Dickson (n.d.).
    - John Henry to Joseph Dickson (Box 1, Folder 2)
      John Henry asking Joseph Dickson to let Mr. Jno. Hide have the cow Henry left at Dickson's house (n.d.).
  - Slave Documents, 1793-1810
    - Sale of a Negro man, August 3, 1793 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Sale of a Negro man named Gib from John Dean to Joseph Dickson for 65 pounds.
    - Note of payment, March 23, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Note of payment due for hiring a Negro boy named Patten from John Carpenter to Joseph Dickson.
    - Agreement, September 21, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Agreement between Jno. H. Flood(?) and Joseph Dickson as to the transfer of a "Negroe Woman" named Nan and two children for $5.
    - Note of payment, September 27, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Note of payment of 110 pounds for the sale of a Negro boy named Elijah due to Joseph Dickson from John Ewdend of Rockbridge County, Virginia.
    - Note of payment, December 8, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Note of payment of 130 pounds from the sale of a Negro boy named Joel from Joel Walker of Greenbrier County, Virginia, to Joseph Dickson.
    - Transfer of a slave notice, October 1809 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Transfer of a "Negro Girl slave" named Jude from Catherine McClung to Joseph Dickson.
    - Sale of a slave to Joseph Dickson, October 20, 1809 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Sale of "Jeff, a Mulatto slave," to Joseph Dickson for 51 pounds from Catherine McClung.
    - Sale of a slave to Joseph Dickson, June 11, 1810 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Sale of "Jane, a Negro woman slave," for $300, by James Kincaide to Joseph Dickson.
  - Bonds and Contracts, 1773-1822
    - Transfer of debt, December 2, 1773 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Transfer of debt of Joseph Dickson from John Murray of Philadelphia County, Pennsylvania, to John Dickenson of Augusta County, Virginia.
    - Contract, June 7, 1774 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Contract of James Connelly to pay John Dickenson twenty-two pounds.
    - Contract, June 7, 1774 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Contract of John and Joseph Dickson to pay John Dickenson 200 pounds owed.
    - Promise note, February 19, 1776 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Promise of Joseph Dickson of Botetourt County, Virginia, to pay Leonard Beall of Augusta County, Virginia, fifteen pounds owed.
    - Contract, February 29, 1776 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Contract of Robert Armstrong and John Scott to pay John Bollar eighteen pounds "Good and Lawfull money of Virginia."
    - Promise note, February 27, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Promise of Joseph Dickson of of Botetourt County, Virginia, to pay Joseph Baley 125 pounds owed.
    - Contract, September 18, 1781 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Contract for Jacob Rife to pay Jos. Dickson 100 pounds owed.
    - Contract, June 4, 1783 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Contract for unknown to pay Henry Gaye one pound.
    - Contract, July 3, 1789 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Contract of James Riddle of Augusta County, Virginia, to pay Joseph Dickson of Greenbrier County, Virginia, four pounds.
    - Receipt, March 9, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Receipt for a bond from Jos. Dickson to John Nivins.
    - Contract, May 20, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Contract of Joseph Dickson to pay James Black fifty pounds owed.
    - Promise note, September 25, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Promise of unknown to pay James Humphries eight pounds owed.
    - Contract, December 25, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Contract for unknown to pay George Stuart six pounds owed.
    - Contract, June 5, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Contract of indenture of Joseph Dickson's son John to apprentice as a tailor to Hugh Paul for five years.
    - Contract, September 29, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Contract for Joseph Dickson, Jacob Vanosdol, Levin Gibson, and Samuel Kincaid to appraise the estate of James Humphries deceased and make a report to the court.
    - Contract, September 27, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Contract of Joseph Dickson to pay John Ederds(?) twenty-five pounds owed.
    - Contract, February 28, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Contract of John Atkinson of Greenbrier County, Virginia, to pay Joseph Dickson 1000 pounds owed.
    - Acknowledgement, August 16, 1803 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Acknowledgement of John Dickson's receipt of "an old pocket book containing two Bonds" from John Staufler(?) and Jno. Deem.
    - Contract, February 6, 1804 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Contract of indenture of Joseph Dickson's son George to apprentice as a gunsmith to Nathaniel Kelly.
    - Contract, September 19, 1804 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Contract to release Joseph Dickson of a debt of 350 pounds to Richard Dickson of Greenbrier County, Virginia, due to the loss of the previous contract.
    - Deed, August 14, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Deed of release from Nancy Dickson, widow of Joseph, to relinquish all rights to the provisions made in her husband's will, turn over his estate to her son Robert, and live off an allowance allocated by her son.
  - Deeds and Land Transfer Records, 1772-1817, n.d.
    - Transfer of land, July 22, 1772 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Transfer of a tract of land from John McClinachan to John Davis for twenty-seven pounds.
    - Sale of land, June 9, 1773 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Sale of a tract of land from John Davis to Joseph Dixon for thirty-seven pounds.
    - Copy of a grant (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Copy of a grant from 1774 to James Ewing for a tract of land in Botetourt County, Virginia, from John Earl of Dunmore.
    - Agreement, September 10, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Agreement from Joseph Dickson allowing William Crow to live on a certain tract of land owned by Dickson.
    - Transfer of land, October 11, 1781 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Transfer of a tract of land from John Douckwaler of Greenbrier County, Virginia, to Jacob Rife.
    - Exchange of a horse, August 14, 1786 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Exchange of a horse owned by Thos. Dunwody to Joseph Dickson for a tract of land.
    - Transfer of land, March 25, 1788 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Transfer of land from Henry Childers to Joseph Dickson.
    - Statement, June 10, 1788 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Statement of debt of 140 pounds from Joseph Dickson to William Crawford for the transfer of land of Honards Creek.
    - Promise, December 2, 1789 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Promise to deliver thirty acres of land on Honards Creek to Elweis Atwater from Joseph Dickson(?).
    - Deed, January 25, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Deed of land sold from William Dinwiddie (Dunwoodey?) and his wife Elizabeth to Joseph Dixon.
    - Transfer of ownership, April 16, 1792 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Transfer of ownership of a tract of land from John Nevins to Joseph Dickson.
    - Sale of land, November 19, 1793 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Sale of a tract of land from Joseph Dickson to Jacob Clangman and William Dunwoody.
    - Contract, May 20, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Contract for payment due from the sale of a tract of land from Joseph Dickson to James Black and William McClung.
    - Deed, July 8, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Deed of land sold by James Black and his wife Rachel to Joseph Dickson.
    - Sale of land, December 2, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Sale of land from George Stuart to Joseph Dickson.
    - Sale of land, March 29, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Sale of 125 acres to William McClung from Joseph Dickson.
    - Transfer of land, June 21, 1803 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Transfer of land owned by Donal Alison of Greenbrier County, Virginia, to Joseph Dickson for 100 pounds.
    - Sale of land, December 27, 1803 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Sale of land from Joseph Dickson to Lewis Shalman.
    - Receipt, February 9, 1804 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Receipt for sum of $50 to Daniel Allison from Joseph Dickson in payment for land sold.
    - Deed, July 31, 1804 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Deed of land sold to Joseph Dickson Jr. from his father.
    - Deed, April 9, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Deed of bargain and sale from William Morris and Allen Taylor to William Rennick for 800 acres in unknown area.
    - Contract, November 11, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Contract binding Frederick Hoober to paying Joseph Dickson 220 pounds owed for a one-fourth acre lot in Lewisburgh, Greenbrier County, Virginia.
    - Deed, November 26, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Deed for a lot of land in Lewisburg, Greenbrier County, Virginia, to Joseph Dickson from Richard Tyne and his wife Sarah, signed by John Stuart.
    - Receipt, November 20, 1806 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Receipt for a "patton of land" of seventy acres from Joseph Dickson to Jacob Winslow(?).
    - Contract, July 7, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Contract to rent land to James Mayer from Joseph Dickson.
    - Memorandum (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Memorandum concerning obtaining a copy of Ewings deed from the Greenbrier office, and distributing it to Edward Rumsey, Allen Taylor, William Morris, and James Byrnside (n.d.).
  - Horses, Livestock, and Property, 1775-1811, n.d.
    - Receipt, January 25, 1775 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Receipt from the sale of a white mare from Joseph Dickson to John Young for seven pounds.
    - Contract, March 25, 1788 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Contract for the sale of a "hourse" from Honery Childers(?) to Joseph Dickson.
    - Receipt, August 13, 1788 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Receipt of the sale of a mare from Joseph Dickson to William Jeres(?) in exchange for work done by Jeres.
    - Contract, September 23, 1788 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Contract for transfer of two mares and a horse William Crawford received from Joseph Dickson.
    - Receipt, January 7, 1789 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Receipt for transfer of a bay horse from Henry Banks to John Nivins.
    - Receipt, May 19, 1789 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Receipt for a bay mare sold by Joseph Dickson to Samuel Miller.
    - Receipt, April 17, 1790 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Receipt for the payment of forty shillings for work done by Richard Masters for Joseph Dickson.
    - Contract, September 10, 1790 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Contract for William Wallace of Wythe County, Virginia, to pay 290 pounds to James Black for the sale of two mares, with the promise that if Wallace was not able to pay the stated smount he would give Black two slaves.
    - Request, September 25, 1790 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Request for M. Edgar to the unknown recipient of the note to give Mr. Kyle a cow, and Edgar would settle the sale with Mr. Hagreth.
    - Receipt, June 12, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Receipt for three pounds in payment for the services of a stud horse owned by Joseph Anderson to Joseph Dickson.
    - Receipt, June 15, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Receipt for the sale of a bay mare from Rueben Wade of Goochland County, Virginia, to Joseph Dickson.
    - Receipt, July 8, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Receipt for the sale of a black horse to David Alle(?) to Joseph Dickson.
    - Sale of a horse, November 21, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Sale of a horse from Charles Simmons of Bedford County to Joseph Dickson.
    - Sale of a bay mare, August 26, 1799 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Sale of a bay mare from Thomas Reid to Joseph Dickson.
    - Sale of a mare, October 21, 1799 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Sale of a mare from Joseph Dickson to James Rollens.
    - Receipt, May 4, 1801 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Receipt for the sale of a cow from James Blagg to Joseph Dickson.
    - Sale of a mare, June 3, 1801 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Sale of a mare from Wm. McClunson(?) to Joseph Dickson.
    - Contract, September 7, 1802 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Contract between James Anderson and Dorel Jere(?) for the transfer of cattle, witnessed by Joseph Dickson.
    - Sale of a heifer, January 30, 1804 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Sale of a heifer from Samuel Dedman of Kentucky to Joseph Dickson.
    - Receipt, September 22, 1804 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Receipt for a cow from Joseph Dickson sold to John Hyde.
    - Receipt, October 30, 1811 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Receipt for six head of cattle purchased from Joseph Dickson by Michael Baskal(?).
    - Contract, July 22, 1813 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Contract to exchange a mare owned by James Hammand for a black horse owned by Joseph Dickson.
    - Sale of a draft (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Sale of a draft (horse?) from unknown to Jacob Rife (n.d.).
    - Financial accounts, 1771-1779 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Financial accounts, 1771-79; 22 items. Receipts for money received.
    - Financial accounts, 1779, 1780-1789 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Financial accounts, 1780-89; 27 items. Household goods purchased, receipt for 1779 taxes paid by Dickson.
    - Financial accounts, 1790-1799 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Financial accounts, 1790-99; 34 items.
    - Financial accounts, 1800-1805 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Financial accounts, 1800-05; 35 items; includes bill for tuition of Dickson's children to "English school."
    - Financial accounts, 1806-1809 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Financial accounts, 1806-09; 19 items.
    - Financial accounts, 1810 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Financial accounts, 1810; 10 items.
    - Financial accounts, 1815, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Financial accounts, 1815, n.d.; 16 items.
    - Tables, 1791(?) (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Currency conversion tables (pounds to dollars), 1791(?).
    - Account book/diary, 1806-1863 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Account book/diary, 1806-63 (includes entries by Robert Dickson).
- John Dickson, 1737-1809
  Papers (1775-1810, n.d.); 20 items (including medical cure recipes for the flux, rheumatism, "stomic ake," snake bite, colic, and others, and accounts, receipts, and a warrant from James Alexander to the sheriff of Monroe County, Virginia, concerning John Dickson).
- Robert Dickson, 1795-1876
  - Correspondence, 1824-1870, n.d.
    - Items, 1824-1848 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      15 items.
    - Items, 1850-1859 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      33 items.
    - Items, 1860-1865 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      36 items (includes a letter from the tax collector of the 62nd Virginia district demanding payment of Dickson's 1863 Confederate taxes; and the draft of a letter, dated September 18, 1865, from Robert Dickson to President Andrew Johnson, vowing his allegiance to the government of the U.S.A. and asking for a "release from the penalties and forfictures to which I am exposed.")
    - Items, 1866-1867 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      24 items (includes a letter from people asking to rent a room with the Dicksons at the White Sulphur Springs.)
    - Items, 1868-1870 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      13 items (includes a letter from J.H.H. Grandy with information about the impact of Reconstruction on the area.)
    - Items (Box 1, Folder 23)
      18 items, with 25 envelopes, n.d..
  - Legal Documents, 1860-1867, n.d.
    - Items, 1800-1849 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      27 items (includes a contract signed by Nancy Dickson relinquishing all claim to her husband's will to her son Robert.)
    - Items, 1850-1859 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      21 items (includes renewals of a contract with Lucian F. Cox, employed by Robert Dickson.)
    - Items, 1861-1867 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      22 items (includes insurance and income tax forms.)
    - Items (Box 1, Folder 27)
      7 items, n.d..
  - Financial Accounts, 1861-1867, n.d.
    - Items, 1816-1829 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      35 items (contains several receipts from Nancy Dickson for her yearly allowance from her son Robert.)
    - Items, 1830-1834 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      45 items (includes accounts from 1833 relating to the labor and supplies incurred during the building of "Locust Hill," the Dickson family home.)
    - Items, 1835-1839 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      63 items.
    - Items, 1840-1842 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      50 items.
    - Items, 1843-1844 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      29 items.
    - Items, 1845-1847 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      32 items.
    - Items, 1848-1849 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      42 items.
    - Items, 1850-1853 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      46 items.
    - Items, 1854-1856 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      57 items.
    - Items, 1857-1859 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      38 items (includes a receipt for Dickson's 1857 taxes.)
    - Items, 1860-1864 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      56 items.
    - Items, 1865-1867 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      21 items (includes a January 1865 bill for $15 in exchange for 500 pounds of hay given by Dickson to the Confederate States of America, and a March 1865 request for four bay mules for use by the CSA.)
    - Items (Box 1, Folder 40)
      52 items, n.d..
- Robert Renick Dickson, 1827-1888
  - Financial accounts., 1849-1869, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 41)
    44 items.
  - Account books, 1843-1880 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    11 items.
  - Transcript, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Sallie Dickson (Robert Rennick's wife)--trial transcript, Sallie Dickson vs. H.F. Dickson, ca. 1916.
- Henry Frazier Dickson, 1841-1909
  - Correspondence, 1864-1924, n.d.
    - Items, 1864-1870 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      21 items.
    - Items, 1871-1874 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Items, 1880-1892 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      26 items.
    - Items, 1905-1924, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 4)
      27 items (includes correspondence from/to Laura Dickson, his wife.)
  - Land deeds and official documents, 1837-1905, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    15 items (includes indenture contracts [1837, 1839, 1846] for land in Monroe County, Virginia.)